Guide to the Joe Jeff Goldblatt Papers, 1984-1997 MS2063
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Joe Jeff Goldblatt papers
1984-1997
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Goldblatt, Joe Jeff
MS2063
4 Linear Feet
Collection contains photographs, slides, audiocassettes, manuscript galleys, correspondence, photograph releases, clippings, book contract, press releases, and media guidelines. This material dates from 1984-97. The material relates to the production and publication of Mr. Goldblatt's books "Special Events: The Art and Science of Celebration" (published by Van Nostrand Reinhold in 1990), "Dictionary of Events Management" (edited with Carol McKibben, published by John Wiley and Sons, 1996) and "Special Events: the Best Practices in Modern Event Management" (published by John Wiley and Sons, 1997).
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Joe Jeff Goldblatt and his wife, Nancy Lynner, donated materials relating to the production and publication of Special Events: The Art and Science of Celebration to the Gelman Library in 1994. In 1997, materials concerning the publication of the Dictionary of Events Management and Special Event: the Best Practices in Modern Event Management were donated as an accretion to the original collection. At the time of the initial donation, Mr. Goldblatt and Ms. Lynner transferred all rights, such as they held them to the collection materials to The George Washington University.
Biographical Note
Joe Jeff Goldblatt (1952- ) was a member of The George Washington University faculty and the founding director of The Event Management Program at the University. Dr. Goldblatt is the author, co author, or editor of six books including the first text book in the field of event management studies (Special Events, the Art and Science of Celebration, published by Van Nostrand Reinhold in 1990). He is responsible for establishing Event Management as a field of study in higher education and the courses he developed are currently being taught in seven different Universities in five countries. He has appeared on more than 500 radio and television programs and is the recipient of the only lifetime achievement award given for contributions in the field of event management by the International Special Events Society. Currently, he is the president of The Goldblatt Company, Inc. which he founded in 1990 as an event management consulting organization. He was the executive producer of The Wonder Company from 1976 to 1990, a special events firm that produced large scale events for corporations, associations, and governments. Goldblatt was also the founding president of the International Special Events Society (ISES) and served as its first president in 1987. In 1993, the ISES awarded Goldblatt the Certified Special Events Professional (CSEP) designation.
Goldblatt is the son of the late Max and Rosa Goldblatt, and was raised in Dallas, Texas. His father was a city councilman in Dallas for two terms and one of the founders of the Dallas County Community College system. Joe Jeff Goldblatt received a Bachelor of Fine Arts degree from St. Edward's University in 1975, with a major in theatre. He earned a Masters of Tourism Administration from The George Washington University in 1994, and earned the doctor of education (Ed.D.) degree at the same university in 1996. Goldblatt is married to Nancy Lynner and they have two sons. Over the years, Joe Jeff Goldblatt has been involved in producing hundreds of special events and shares his expertise through educational resources offered at the university level. He has also written numerous articles in trade and professional journals on event management. His published works include Special Events, the Art and Science of Celebration (published in English and Korean) and the second edition entitled, Special Events: Best Practices in Modern Event Management. He has also published The Ultimate Party Handbook, The Ultimate Guide to Sport Event Management and Marketing (co authored by Stedman Graham and Lisa Delpy Nierotti, Ph.D), Dollars and Events (with Frank Supovitz), and The Dictionary of Event Management (with Carol McKibben). In addition, Goldblatt is currently a member of the editorial board for the Journal of Event Management. Management and Event Tourism Journal.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains photographs, slides, audiocassettes, manuscript galleys, correspondence, photograph releases, clippings, book contract, press releases, and media guidelines. This material dates from 1984-97. The material relates to the production and publication of Mr. Goldblatt's books "Special Events: The Art and Science of Celebration" (published by Van Nostrand Reinhold in 1990), "Dictionary of Events Management" (edited with Carol McKibben, published by John Wiley and Sons, 1996) and "Special Events: the Best Practices in Modern Event Management" (published by John Wiley and Sons, 1997).
This collection is part of the Event Management and Marketing Archives. This archives was established to support the Forum for Sport and Event Management and Marketing of the International Institute of Tourism Studies at The George Washington University.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Special Events: The Art and Science of Celebration; Dictionary of Event Management; Special Events: The Best Practices in Modern Event Management.
Collection note
from the original finding aid: Special Events: the Best Practices in Modern Event Management is the professional, second edition of Goldblatt's earlier work, Special Events: The Art and Science of Celebration. To avoid confusion between the two editions, this finding aid and the headings written on each folder of the collection will refer to the first edition as Art and Science of Celebration" and the second edition as "Best Practices in Modern Event Management". The Goldblatt materials are grouped together by the title of the book to which they relate. Thus there are three major groupings: Art and Science of Celebration
Photographs; Washington (D.C.); Books; Events; Color slides; Audiocassettes; Goldblatt, Joe Jeff; George Washington University. Event Management Program; George Washington University
- Special Events: The Art and Science of Celebration, 1988-1990; MS2063 Series 1; 3 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence, research notes, production schedules, chapter outlines, black and white and color photographs, press materials, contract for publication, clippings, draft manuscripts of chapters and the glossary, final chapter proofs, memoranda, invoices, illustrations, photograph captions, copy-edited manuscripts, and audiocassettes. The material dates from 1988-90. This material relates to the production and publication of Goldblatt's book "Special Events: The Art and Science of Celebration. The audiocassettes are interviews Goldblatt conducted with professionals in the special events field during the fall of 1988. Prominent figures that were interviewed include: Jack Morton, Barnett Lipton, Gene Donati, Robert Jani, as well as many other professionals from the United States, Canada, and England involved with the management and promotion of special events. There are also audiocassettes of orations by speakers at professional conferences on the topics of public presentation and success strategies in relationship to special events.
  - Book Production and Publication: Book proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book Production and Publication: Chapter outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book Production and Publication: Book contract, 06/08/1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book Production and Publication: Tentative book schedule, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book Production and Publication: Book research - note cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Book Production and Publication: Book research - author's notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Book Production and Publication: Book research - author's notes for interviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Book Production and Publication: Book research - interview schedule, 09/29/1988-11/09/1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Book Production and Publication: Book research - miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Book Production and Publication: Van Nostrand Reinhold author information, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book Production and Publication: Van Nostrand Reinhold author questionnaire, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Book Production and Publication: Van Nostrand Reinhold Pulitzer Prize nomination, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Book Production and Publication: Correspondence, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book Production and Publication: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book Production and Publication: Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Book Production and Publication: Permissions lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Book Production and Publication: Copies of permissions to quote, 07/21/1988-11/04/1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Book Production and Publication: Photograph release requests, 08/02/1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Book Production and Publication: Photograph release requests, 08/02/1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Book Production and Publication: Photograph permissions, 08/1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Book Production and Publication: Photograph rejections, 08/02/1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Book Production and Publication: Book contributor lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Book Production and Publication: Publicity and press releases, 05/10/1990-07/25/1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Book Production and Publication: Marketing leads, 05/01/1990-08/10/1990 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Book Production and Publication: Reception and media guidelines, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Book Production and Publication: Clippings, 06/27/1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Dedication and Appreciation, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Preface, 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Introduction, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Introduction, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Introduction (incomplete), 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 1, Your Future in Special Events, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 1, Your Future in Special Events, 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 2, Today's Special Events Industry, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 2, Today's Special Events Industry, 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 3, Planning Events, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 3, Planning Events, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 3, Planning Events, 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 5, Decorating Ideas, 11/08/1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 5, Decorating Ideas (incomplete), 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 5, Decorating Ideas, 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 6, Lighting for Events, 07/13/1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 13, Event Amenities or Necessities?, 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 14, Music, 05/15/1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Chapter 23, Social Events, 07/11/1989 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Glossary, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Glossary, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Glossary, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Glossary, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Resource section, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Resource section, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Additions to resource section, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Book Manuscript: Draft Manuscript: Appendix, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Preliminary material, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Introduction, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 1, Your Future in Special Events, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 2, Today's Special Events Industry, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 3, Planning Events, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 4, Creating the Environment, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 5, Decorating Ideas, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 6, Lighting for Events, 07/13/1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 7, Sound for Events, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 8, Video and Film Production for Events, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 9, Special Effects for Events, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 10, High Technology, 07/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 11, Catering, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 12, Events as Pubic Relations Tools, 07/10/1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 13, Event Amenities - Niceties or Necessities?, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 14, Music for Events, 05/15/1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 15, Entertainment, 07/12/1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 16, Recording Events, 05/31/1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 17, The Business of Special Events, 06/24/1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 18, Theme Parks, 06/07/1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Text captions and Figures, 05/15/1989-06/07/1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 19, Awards Ceremonies, 06/08/1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 20, Opening Ceremonies, 06/14/1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 21, Hospitality, 06/19/1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 22, Ceremonial Events, 06/24/1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 23, Social Events, 07/11/1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 24, Retail Special Events, 07/12/1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 25, Holidays and Special Observations, 06/28/1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 26, Fairs, Festivals, and Public Events, 06/30/1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 27, Sporting Events, 06/29/1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 28, Corporate Events, 07/12/1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 29, Meetings and Conventions, 07/13/1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 30, Special Events as a Management Tool, 07/15/1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Chapter 31, Special Events and Social Change, 07/15/1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: References, Glossary, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Glossary, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Glossary, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Glossary, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Appendix, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Book Manuscript: Copy-Edited Manuscript: Appendix, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Book Manuscript: Manuscript Galleys: Chapter 5, Decorating Ideas, 03/01/1990 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Book Manuscript: Manuscript Galleys: Chapter 6, Lighting for Events, 03/01/1990 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Book Manuscript: Manuscript Galleys: Chapter 23, Social Events, 03/05/1990 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Book Manuscript: Manuscript Galleys: Photograph captions, 02/22/1990 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Photographs and Figures: Drawing for Figure 8.1, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photographs and Figures: Photocopies of possible book photographs and figures, 08/17/1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs and Figures: Draft layout of color photograph section, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photographs and Figures: Draft of photograph captions, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Photographs and Figures: Color Photograph Section: Color slide and draft caption for photograph 1 1984 Olympics Closing Ceremonies, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photographs and Figures: Color Photograph Section: Color slide, print, and draft caption for photograph 2, Korean hotel grand opening, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photographs and Figures: Color Photograph Section: Color print for photograph 3, banquet on Ark Royal aircraft carrier, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and Figures: Color Photograph Section: Color print and draft caption for photograph 4, 50th birthday party at toy museum (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Photographs and Figures: Color Photograph Section: Color slides and prints for photographs 5A, Wizard of Oz characters, and 5B, man with flamingo, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photographs and Figures: Color Photograph Section: Color print and draft caption for photograph 6, Leeds Castle from under marquee, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photographs and Figures: Color Photograph Section: Color print and draft caption for photograph 8, balloon guitar, Rivergate Mall grand opening, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Photographs and Figures: Color Photograph Section: Color print and draft caption for photograph 11, tent lighting, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Photographs and Figures: Black and White Photograph Section: Color print and draft caption for photograph 1, Cinderella USO float, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Photographs and Figures: Black and White Photograph Section: Color print and draft caption for photograph 4, "White House" set, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Photographs and Figures: Black and White Photograph Section: Color print for photograph 5, tent lighting, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Photographs and Figures: Black and White Photograph Section: Color print and draft caption for photograph 6, formal dinner, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Photographs and Figures: Black and White Photograph Section: Color print and draft caption for photograph 7, banquet room with visible first food service, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Photographs and Figures: Black and White Photograph Section: Color slide, black and white and color prints, and draft caption for photograph 8, wizard/magician, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide, print, and draft caption of floral American flag over Vietnam War Memorial, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide, print, and draft caption of "Punchline Premier,", undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide, print, and draft caption of 1989 NFL Super Bowl Halftime Show, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide, print, and draft caption of Dupont "game show" meeting, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color prints and draft caption of couple with helicopter, 3 prints, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide and draft caption of lighted "Capitol-type" building, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print and draft caption of Digital luncheon, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print and draft caption of battle re-enactment at Ripley Castle, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide, print, and draft caption of actor-"Vaudevillian Act" [sic], undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide, print, and draft caption of Manassas Mall portable stage, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print, invitation, and draft caption of Matsumoto-Fulton wedding, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print and draft caption of banquet at London's Guild Hall, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Black and white print and draft caption of Bernard Sullivan and the Duke of Edinburgh, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Black and white print and draft caption of Lester Lanin leading orchestra, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print and draft caption of three waiters pouring champagne at Chicago Hilton, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide (4"x5") and draft caption of fireworks over Ripley Castle, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide, print, and draft caption of video cameraman, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print and draft caption of banquet in natural history museum, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print and draft caption of lighted entryway, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print and draft caption of "We the People" float, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color print and draft caption of balconied theatre set, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color prints of Royal Ark aircraft carrier, 2 prints, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Draft caption for unused photograph (no photograph accompaniment), undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Photographs and Figures: Unused Photographs: Color slide, unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Tent Rental Report, 06/1988 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Invoice, 07/23/1990 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Memoranda, 07/26/1990 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - How to Select a Special Events Producer; Basic Tools, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Oversize: Book Manuscript: Typesetter's copy of References and Glossary, 06/04/1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Oversize: Photographs and Figures: olor print and draft caption for photograph 7, dune buggy/surfing set, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Oversize: Photographs and Figures: Color print and draft caption for photograph 9, lighted set with Sydney Opera House/sails, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Oversize: Photographs and Figures: Color print and draft caption for photograph 10, pink balloon centerpieces, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)